<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Clin Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijcp</journal-id><journal-title>International Journal of Clinical Practice</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1368-5031</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1742-1241</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17362472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1920547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-1241.2007.01338.x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of budesonide/formoterol maintenance and reliever therapy on asthma exacerbations</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manjra</surname><given-names>A I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jorup</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naya</surname><given-names>I P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>N E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buhl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pneumonology and Allergy, Barlicki University Hospital, Medical University of Lodz</institution><addr-line>Lodz, Poland</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Thoracic Medicine, Concord Hospital</institution><addr-line>Concord, Australia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Paediatric Allergy and Asthma Centre, Westville Hospital</institution><addr-line>Westville, South Africa</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>AstraZeneca</institution><addr-line>Lund, Sweden</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Allergy and Immunology, Hospital 1&#x000b0; de Octubre, ISSSTE</institution><addr-line>Mexico City, Mexico</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>Pulmonary Department, Mainz University Hospital</institution><addr-line>Mainz, Germany</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to</bold>: Piotr Kuna, Division of Pneumonology and Allergy, Barlicki University Hospital, Medical University of Lodz, Lodz, Poland Tel.: + 48&#x000a0;(0)42&#x000a0;6776&#x000a0;834 Fax: + 48&#x000a0;(0)42&#x000a0;6781&#x000a0;176 Email: <email>pkuna@bg.p.lodz.pl</email></corresp><fn><p><bold>Disclosures</bold> PK was reimbursed by GlaxoSmithKline, AstraZeneca, Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme, Ivax and Boehringer Ingelheim for attending several international conferences in 2004, 2005 and 2006. PK participated as a speaker in scientific meetings and courses organised and financed by various pharmaceutical companies (GlaxoSmithKline, AstraZeneca, Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme, Ivax, Boehringer Ingelheim, Altana, Nexter, Allergopharma, Polpharma, Novartis) and participated in advisory board meetings for GlaxoSmithKline, Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme and Boehringer Ingelheim. The institution where PK is employed received a research grant from Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme in 2004. MP has received support for travel to international conferences from AstraZeneca and GlaxoSmithKline, and remuneration for serving on advisory boards and speaking at educational meetings for AstraZeneca and GlaxoSmithKline. MP has provided expert witness testimony for AstraZeneca. AM served on the advisory board for AstraZeneca and Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme between 2003 and 2004. AM was reimbursed for serving on the AstraZeneca advisory board. AM has been reimbursed for delivering lectures for AstraZeneca, Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme and Novartis. CJ and IN are employed by AstraZeneca and hold shares in the company. NEMJ has not declared any conflict of interest. RB has received reimbursement for attending scientific conferences and/or fees for speaking at CME conferences and/or consulting from Altana, Astellas, AstraZeneca, Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, Fujisawa, GlaxoSmithKline, Merck, Sharpe &#x00026; Dohme, Novartis, Pfizer, Schering Plough and Zambon. The Pulmonary Department at Mainz University Hospital, where RB is employed, received financial compensation for services performed during participation in single- and multi-centre clinical phase I&#x02013;IV trials organised by various pharmaceutical companies.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>61</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Authors Journal compilation 2007 Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><abstract><p>This randomised, double-blind, 6-month study compared budesonide/formoterol for maintenance and relief with salmeterol/fluticasone and a fixed maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol, both with terbutaline for relief. Following a 2-week run-in, 3335 symptomatic adults and adolescents (mean FEV<sub>1</sub> 73% predicted, mean inhaled corticosteroid dose 745 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day) received budesonide/formoterol 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid plus additional inhalations as needed, salmeterol/fluticasone 25/125 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g two inhalations bid plus as-needed terbutaline or budesonide/formoterol 320/9 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid plus as-needed terbutaline. Budesonide/formoterol for maintenance and relief prolonged the time to first severe exacerbation requiring hospitalisation, emergency room treatment or oral steroids (primary variable) vs. fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone and budesonide/formoterol (p = 0.0034 and p = 0.023 respectively; log-rank test). Exacerbation rates were 19, 16 and 12 events/100 patients/6 months for salmeterol/fluticasone, fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol and budesonide/formoterol for maintenance and relief, respectively, [rate reduction vs. fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone (0.61; 95% CI 0.49&#x02013;0.76, p &#x0003c; 0.001) and vs. fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol (0.72; 95% CI 0.57&#x02013;0.90, p = 0.0048)]. Budesonide/formoterol maintenance and relief patients used less inhaled corticosteroid vs. salmeterol/fluticasone and fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol patients. All treatments provided similar marked improvements in lung function, asthma control days and asthma-related quality of life. Budesonide/formoterol for maintenance and relief reduces asthma exacerbations and maintains similar daily asthma control at a lower overall drug load compared with fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone and budesonide/formoterol.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="bx1" position="float"><sec><title>What's known</title><p>Clinical evidence has shown that asthma management using budesonide/formoterol (Symbicort&#x000ae;) maintenance and reliever therapy (SMART) provides a simpler and more effective treatment strategy than traditional approaches with short-acting <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist (SABA) therapy. SMART improves daily symptom control and prevents severe exacerbations more effectively than higher doses of inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) plus SABA or the same maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol plus as-needed terbutaline or formoterol. The SMART approach has been recommended in the recent GINA guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>What's new</title><p>The evidence within this manuscript confirms that patients randomised to receive SMART therapy have greater protection from severe asthma exacerbations, including hospitalisations and emergency room treatment, than those treated even with higher traditional fixed-dose ICS/long-acting <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist (LABA) treatment. Similar levels of daily asthma symptom control were observed compared with treatment with salmeterol/fluticasone or fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol. The observed improvements in overall asthma control occurred despite a 50% reduction in regular maintenance doses of ICS/LABA with the SMART approach.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The current treatment recommended by guidelines for persistent asthma is a fixed-dose inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) or an ICS/long-acting <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist (LABA) combination administered twice daily (bid), plus a short-acting <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist (SABA) as needed for symptom relief. The two ICS/LABA combination inhalers currently available &#x02013; budesonide/formoterol and salmeterol/fluticasone &#x02013; are highly effective at providing early and sustained improvements in asthma control for patients symptomatic on ICS alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>).</p><p>Even with such treatments, asthma control remains suboptimal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Residual asthma symptoms can persist, even in patients using regular ICS or ICS/LABA maintenance therapy, with exacerbations ranging from mild increases in symptoms to events requiring medical intervention or hospitalisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). Consequently, asthma management plans have been developed that specify treatment changes in response to increasing symptoms or deteriorating lung function. These effectively reduce the rate of exacerbations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), but require detailed physician guidance and patient adherence. Despite strong advocacy and evidence of effectiveness, the use of asthma management plans remains disappointingly low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>).</p><p>A new approach to asthma therapy is budesonide/formoterol (Symbicort&#x000ae;) maintenance and reliever therapy (SMART) using one inhaler, without the requirement for a separate SABA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). This novel treatment approach has also been endorsed in the latest Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) guidelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>). The simple substitution of budesonide/formoterol for SABA allows the dose of controller medication, LABA and ICS, to be increased quickly in response to symptoms, while simultaneously offering rapid symptom relief. A previous study has shown that SMART is more effective at reducing exacerbations and improving daily asthma control than the same maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol plus as-needed SABA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). In that study, however, SMART patients used, on average, a higher daily dose of budesonide/formoterol than fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol patients. Therefore, a comparison of the efficacy of SMART with that of a higher maintenance dose of ICS/LABA was needed to answer two remaining questions: could SMART be as effective at reducing exacerbations as a higher fixed maintenance dose of combination therapy and would SMART result in greater day-to-day fluctuations in asthma control?</p><p>Using a double-blind approach, we hypothesised that SMART (budesonide/formoterol 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid plus additional as-needed inhalations for relief) would prevent exacerbations more effectively than a fixed dose of salmeterol/fluticasone (25/125 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g two inhalations bid) plus terbutaline or a comparable fixed maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol (320/9 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid) plus terbutaline as needed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>), and that this important benefit would not be achieved at the expense of daily asthma control.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>In this study (study code SD-039-0735), outpatients aged &#x02265; 12 years with a diagnosis of asthma [as defined by the American Thoracic Society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>)] for &#x02265; 6 months and using ICS for &#x02265; 3 months [&#x02265; 500 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day of budesonide or fluticasone (or &#x02265; 1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day of another ICS) for &#x02265; 1 month] were eligible for enrolment. Patients had to have a forced expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV<sub>1</sub>) &#x02265; 50% predicted normal with &#x02265; 12% reversibility following terbutaline 1 mg and &#x02265; 1 asthma exacerbation in the previous 1&#x02013;12 months. Patients using reliever medication on &#x02265; 5 of the last 7 days of the 2-week run-in were randomised; those with &#x0003e; 10 as-needed inhalations in any day of run-in and patients who experienced an asthma exacerbation during run-in were not randomised. Patients using systemic corticosteroids or with respiratory infections affecting asthma control within 30 days of study entry were excluded.</p><sec><title>Study design</title><p>This 6-month, randomised, double-blind, double-dummy, parallel-group study was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki and Good Clinical Practice guidelines. Independent ethics committees approved the study protocol, patient information and consent forms. All patients and parents/guardians of adolescents gave written informed consent. The first patient was enrolled on 19 December 2003 and the last patient completed the study on 11 March 2005.</p><p>Patients attended the clinic at the beginning and end of run-in (visits 1&#x02013;2), and after 8, 16 and 24 weeks of treatment (visits 3&#x02013;5 respectively). During run-in, patients used their regular ICS for maintenance and terbutaline (Bricanyl&#x000ae; Turbuhaler&#x000ae;; AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden) for symptom relief. ICS/LABA combination inhalers were stopped 72 h before study entry and the corresponding ICS dose used. Following run-in, eligible patients were randomised to one of three treatment groups for 24 weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Figure 1</xref>): budesonide/formoterol (Symbicort&#x000ae; Turbuhaler&#x000ae;; AstraZeneca, Sweden) 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid for maintenance plus additional inhalations as needed (Symbicort SMART&#x000ae;), fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone [Seretide&#x02122;/Advair&#x02122; Evohaler&#x02122; (pressurised metered-dose inhaler, pMDI), GlaxoSmithKline, Uxbridge, UK] 25/125 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g two inhalations bid plus terbutaline as reliever medication or budesonide/formoterol 320/9 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid plus terbutaline. The salmeterol/fluticasone dose, delivered via a dry-powder inhaler (DPI), has been shown in previous studies to have similar clinical efficacy to the fixed dose of budesonide/formoterol used in this study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>). In addition, therapeutic equivalence has been reported for salmeterol/fluticasone delivered via either DPI or pMDI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>).</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Patient flow. bid, twice daily; ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; maintenance and reliever therapy. Terbutaline dose expressed as 0.5 mg/inhalation metered dose corresponds to 0.4 mg/inhalation delivered dose</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725-f1"/></fig><p>At the start of the study, all patients were instructed in the correct use of the Turbuhaler and the Evohaler devices. As an additional safety precaution, any patient who required &#x0003e; 10 inhalations of reliever medication on any 1 day was asked to contact the investigator for reassessment.</p></sec><sec><title>Randomisation and blinding</title><p>The randomisation schedule was computer-generated at AstraZeneca Research and Development, Charnwood, UK. Within each centre, patients were randomised strictly sequentially as they became eligible. Individual treatment codes and code envelopes (indicating the treatment allocation for each randomised patient) were provided, but code envelopes were to be opened only in case of medical emergencies.</p><p>To maintain the blinding, all patients received three inhalers. Patients were instructed to take one inhalation from the inhaler with the red grip (budesonide/formoterol or placebo Turbuhaler) and two inhalations from the pMDI (salmeterol/fluticasone or placebo Evohaler) upon rising and before going to bed; for symptom relief, as-needed inhalations were to be taken from the inhaler with the white grip (budesonide/formoterol or terbutaline Turbuhaler).</p></sec><sec><title>Efficacy measures</title><p>The primary objective of this study was to compare the efficacy of SMART [budesonide/formoterol (160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid) plus additional inhalations as needed], with salmeterol/fluticasone (25/125 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g two inhalations bid) plus terbutaline (0.4 mg/inhalation as needed). The primary variable was the time to first severe exacerbation. Severe exacerbations were defined as deterioration in asthma resulting in hospitalisation or emergency room (ER) treatment, or the need for oral steroids for &#x02265; 3 days (as judged by the investigator). To ensure that the results obtained were not specific to choice of ICS/LABA combination therapy or delivery device, predefined secondary objectives investigated were a combination of the efficacy of SMART vs. budesonide/formoterol (320/9 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g one inhalation bid) plus terbutaline (0.4 mg/inhalation as needed) both delivered by Turbuhaler, with an additional comparison of the efficacy between the two fixed-dose ICS/LABA regimen. Secondary outcome variables were the total numbers of severe exacerbations; inhalations of as-needed medication; change in morning and evening peak expiratory flow (PEF), FEV<sub>1</sub>, asthma symptom score, nights with awakenings caused by asthma, symptom-free days, as-needed-free days, asthma-control days and the number of mild exacerbations.</p><p>Patients completed a daily diary throughout the study in which they recorded PEF, symptoms, reliever use and intake of maintenance medication. Adherence to prescribed treatment was checked by the investigator at every visit. Daytime and night-time asthma symptom scores, measured on a scale of 0&#x02013;3 (where 0 = no symptoms and 3 = incapacitating symptoms), were also recorded; these scores were summed to obtain the total daily score (range 0&#x02013;6). The percentage of symptom-free days, nights free of awakenings, reliever-free days and asthma control days (a night and a day without asthma symptoms, no night-time awakenings caused by asthma and no reliever use) were calculated from diary-card data. Mild exacerbation days, defined as a day with any one of the following: morning PEF &#x02265; 20% below baseline, daily as-needed medication use &#x02265; 2 inhalations above baseline or a night with an asthma-related awakening, were also calculated from diary-card data. A mild exacerbation was defined as two consecutive mild exacerbation days satisfying the same criterion.</p><p>FEV<sub>1</sub> was assessed by spirometry, performed as recommended by the European Respiratory Society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>), at each clinic visit. The best of three satisfactory FEV<sub>1</sub> tests was recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>). Following instruction, patients recorded morning and evening PEF using a Mini-Wright&#x000ae; peak flow meter (Clement Clarke, Harlow, UK). Measurements were to be carried out before inhalation of the study medication. The highest of three consecutive measurements was recorded.</p><p>The Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ) 5-item version (ACQ-5) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>) and Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire [standardised version; AQLQ(S)] (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>) were self-administered at clinic visits.</p><p>Tolerability was assessed by the recording of adverse events at clinic visits. Investigators were provided with a set of instructions to be used for the interpretation of causality judgement.</p><p>Overall ICS treatment load was compared between groups by converting ICS doses to beclomethasone dipropionate (BDP)-equivalent ICS doses. These calculations were based on the GINA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) estimates of equipotence of ICS doses as metered doses: fluticasone 500 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g = budesonide 800 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g = beclomethasone 1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g; 800 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g budesonide metered dose = 640 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g delivered dose.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The study was powered to detect a difference in the primary end-point (time to first severe exacerbation). With a total of 1000 patients/group, a log-rank test (at the two-sided 5% significance level) had a 90% chance of detecting a difference between treatment groups, assuming a true difference of 20% vs. 14.5% in the proportion of patients experiencing a severe exacerbation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>). All patients with data after randomisation were included in the intention-to-treat population for all efficacy analyses. The safety analyses were based on all patients who received &#x02265; 1 dose of study drug.</p><p>The time to first severe exacerbation was described using Kaplan&#x02013;Meier plots and was compared between treatments using a log-rank test. Further description of treatment differences was obtained using a Cox proportional hazards model stratified by country, with treatment as a factor. The total number of severe exacerbations was compared between treatment groups using a Poisson regression model, with treatment and country as factors and time in the study as an offset variable.</p><p>Changes in diary-card variables from the average value during run-in (average value over the last 10 days of run-in) to the average value during the treatment period were compared between treatments using an analysis of variance (ANOVA) model, with treatment and country as fixed factors and the run-in means as a covariate. Change in FEV<sub>1</sub> from baseline to the average value during visits 3&#x02013;5 was analysed using a similar ANOVA, with baseline values as a covariate. The ACQ and AQLQ(S) overall scores were analysed in the same way as FEV<sub>1</sub>, with the exception that, for AQLQ(S), the change from baseline to the last visit on treatment was used.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Patient profile</title><p>Patient flow is summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Figure 1</xref>. Of the 4399 patients enrolled at 235 centres in 16 countries, 3335 were randomised to treatment. The most common reasons for exclusion from randomisation were failure to meet defined criteria for asthma severity, specifically spirometry criteria and use of as-needed medication during the run-in period. There were 409 protocol deviations in 327 patients, none of which justified exclusion of data from the analysis. Patient demographics are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Self-reported adherence to maintenance medication was high; 99% of patients in all groups reported taking more than 81% of their maintenance medication.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patients&#x02019; baseline characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salmeterol/ fluticasone (<italic>n</italic> = 1123)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budesonide/ formoterol (<italic>n</italic> = 1105)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART (<italic>n</italic> = 1107)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484 (43)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448 (41)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">479 (43)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age, years (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (17)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (17)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265; 18 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">912 (81)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">892 (81)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">908 (82)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;12&#x02013;17 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197 (18)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Smoking status</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">904 (80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">865 (78)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">873 (79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Previous, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Current, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean FEV<sub>1</sub>, % predicted (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (14)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean FEV<sub>1</sub> reversibility, % (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ICS at study entry, <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day (SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">744 (230)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">750 (262)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740 (240)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LABA use at study entry, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">525 (47)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518 (47)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">509 (46)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy; FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in 1 s; ICS, inhaled corticosteroid; LABA, long-acting <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Severe exacerbations</title><p>SMART prolonged the time to first severe exacerbation compared with fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone and budesonide/formoterol (log-rank test p = 0.0034 and p = 0.023 respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Figure 2</xref>). There was a 33% reduction in the hazard ratio (HR) for a first severe exacerbation with SMART compared with salmeterol/fluticasone [HR 0.67; 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.52&#x02013;0.87; p = 0.003] and a 26% reduction compared with fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol (HR 0.74; 95% CI 0.56&#x02013;0.96; p = 0.026). The two fixed-dose groups did not differ with respect to time to first severe exacerbation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The total number of severe asthma exacerbations was reduced by 39% [relative rate (RR) 0.61; 95% CI 0.49&#x02013;0.76; p &#x0003c; 0.001] in the SMART group compared with fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone and by 28% (RR 0.72; 95% CI 0.57&#x02013;0.90; p = 0.0048) compared with fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol. The total number of exacerbations was similar in the two fixed-dose groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figure 3a</xref>).</p><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Time to first severe exacerbation (deterioration in asthma resulting in hospitalisation/emergency room treatment, or the need for oral steroids for &#x02265; 3 days). SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725-f2"/></fig><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Cumulative rate of (A) severe exacerbations and (B) hospitalisations/emergency room treatments caused by asthma; p-values are derived from relative rate analysis (Poisson regression analysis). SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725-f3"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Exacerbation burden</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Treatment comparison of hazard ratios (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exacerbation burden</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salmeterol/fluticasone</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budesonide/formoterol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART vs. salmeterol/fluticasone</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART vs. budesonide/formoterol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budesonide/formoterol vs. salmeterol/fluticasone</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>All event types</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No. patients having at least one severe exacerbation (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.52, 0.87); p = 0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.56, 0.96); p = 0.026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.72, 1.16); p = 0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rate/100 patients/6 months<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.49, 0.76); p &#x0003c; 0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.57, 0.90); p = 0.0048</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.69, 1.04); p = 0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Total no. severe exacerbations (total no. days with event)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (1327)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (1143)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (692)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Hospitalisation/ER treatment</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No. patients having at least one hospitalisation/ER treatment (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.48, 0.99); p = 0.047</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.65, 1.44); p = 0.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.49, 1.02); p = 0.066</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Rate/100 patients/6 months<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.44, 0.83); p = 0.0015</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.63, 1.24); p = 0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.51, 0.92); p = 0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Total no. events (total no. days with event)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (278)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (174)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (108)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><label>*</label><p>Cox proportional hazards model of time to first severe exacerbation</p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Comparisons of relative rates from a Poisson regression. SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy; ER, emergency room.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The total number of hospitalisations/ER treatments was reduced in both budesonide/formoterol groups compared with the fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone group: there was a 39% rate reduction in the SMART group (RR 0.61; 95% CI 0.44&#x02013;0.83; p = 0.0015) and a 32% reduction in the fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol group (RR 0.68; 95% CI 0.51&#x02013;0.92; p = 0.013; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figure 3b</xref>). The difference between the two budesonide/formoterol groups was not statistically significant.</p><p>The total exacerbation burden in days is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>. The total number of days with exacerbations requiring oral steroid use was reduced by 41&#x02013;45% with SMART compared with both fixed-dose regimens. Moreover, compared with fixed-dose treatment, SMART reduced the number of days with exacerbations requiring hospitalisation/ER treatment by 38&#x02013;61% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>A <italic>post hoc</italic> analysis, based on interaction between age-class and treatment, indicated that the size of the reduction in the overall exacerbation rate in the SMART group was consistent for adults (aged &#x02265; 18 years) and adolescents (aged &#x0003c; 18 years) (p = 0.84, interaction test). Adults treated with SMART had a 39% and 29% reduction in severe exacerbations vs. fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone (p &#x0003c; 0.001) and fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol (p = 0.0043) respectively. Similarly, the small number of adolescents treated with SMART had non-statistically significant reductions in severe exacerbations of 42% and 24% respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Mild exacerbations</title><p>No significant differences were seen between the SMART group and the two fixed-dose regimens in the number of mild exacerbation days or the time to a mild exacerbation (two consecutive mild exacerbation days). There was an average of 27 mild exacerbation days/patient/6 months in the salmeterol/fluticasone group, 29 in the fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol group and 27 in the SMART group. Overall, 660 (59%), 689 (63%) and 674 (61%) salmeterol/fluticasone, budesonide/formoterol and SMART patients, respectively, experienced a mild exacerbation.</p></sec><sec><title>Asthma symptoms</title><p>SMART provided similar improvements to fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol and salmeterol/fluticasone in all symptom-control measures used to assess daily variability in asthma control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Clinical outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Treatment comparison of clinical outcomes: mean difference (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efficacy end-point</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salmeterol/fluticasone</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budesonide/formoterol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART vs. salmeterol/ fluticasone</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMART vs. budesonide/ formoterol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budesonide/formoterol vs. salmeterol/fluticasone</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Asthma symptoms</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Total score (0&#x02013;6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (&#x02212;0.03, 0.10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (&#x02212;0.07, 0.06)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (&#x02212;0.02, 0.11)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Symptom-free days (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.5 (&#x02212;5.3, 0.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.8 (&#x02212;3.6, 2.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.6 (&#x02212;4.4, 1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Asthma-control days<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">*</xref> (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.6 (&#x02212;5.4, 0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.7 (&#x02212;3.6, 2.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.9 (&#x02212;4.7, 1.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Night-time awakenings (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.8 (&#x02212;2.4, 0.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0 (&#x02212;2.6, 0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (&#x02212;1.4, 1.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Use of as-needed medication</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Total no. inhalations/day</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (&#x02212;0.02, 0.16)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.03 (&#x02212;0.12, 0.06)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.01, 0.19)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">&#x02020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">As-needed-free days (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.2 (&#x02212;6.0, &#x02212;0.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.8 (&#x02212;4.6, 1.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.4 (&#x02212;4.2, 1.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Lung function</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">FEV<sub>1</sub> (l)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Visit 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006 (&#x02212;0.025, 0.037)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005 (&#x02212;0.026, 0.037)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (&#x02212;0.031, 0.031)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Visit 3&#x02013;5 (mean)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Morning PEF (l/min)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">337</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.2 (&#x02212;6.9, 0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.7 (&#x02212;4.5, 3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.5 (&#x02212;6.2, 1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Evening PEF (l/min)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Run-in</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.3 (&#x02212;4.9, 2.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.6 (&#x02212;4.3, 3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.7 (&#x02212;4.3, 3.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3-1"><label>*</label><p>Asthma-control days were defined as a day with no symptoms (day or night), no awakenings caused by asthma and no as-needed medication use;</p></fn><fn id="tf3-2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Statistically different at the 5% level of significance. SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy; FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in 1 s; PEF, peak expiratory flow; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Asthma questionnaires</title><p>Patients in all three treatment groups reported similar improvements in AQLQ(S) and ACQ-5 scores. Changes of 0.5 units from run-in indicate clinically relevant improvements in both scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). These improvements were indicated by an increase in AQLQ(S) score of 0.76&#x02013;0.78 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Figure 4a</xref>) and the reduction in ACQ-5 score of 0.74&#x02013;0.79 in the three treatment groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Figure 4b</xref>).</p><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Mean overall (A) Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (standardised version) [AQLQ(S)] and (B) Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ) scores over the duration of the study. QoL, quality of life; SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725-f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Lung function</title><p>FEV<sub>1</sub> and PEF values during the run-in and treatment periods are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>. No differences between the three treatment groups in any of these measures were detected.</p></sec><sec><title>Overall treatment load</title><p>As-needed reliever medication use is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>. As-needed use was similar in the SMART and fixed-dose groups, decreasing by 8&#x02013;9 inhalations/week compared with baseline in all three groups. The range of daily mean BDP-equivalent ICS doses [calculations based on GINA estimations of equipotence of ICS in metered doses: fluticasone 500 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g = budesonide 800 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g = beclomethasone 1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>)] for the three treatment groups are summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Figure 5</xref>. While individual mean doses varied in SMART patients as a consequence of the treatment concept, there was an overall reduction in mean ICS dose in the SMART group compared with both fixed-dose groups. The overall number of days per treatment group when oral corticosteroids were required for asthma was 619 days in the SMART group, 1044 days with budesonide/formoterol and 1132 days with salmeterol/fluticasone.</p><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Range of daily mean doses of ICS/LABA reported by individual study patients. *Mean ICS doses converted to BDP equivalents based on GINA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) guidelines. Compared with fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol treatment, 9 : 1 (ratio: 63% divided by 7%) SMART-treated patients reduced their mean daily dose by at least 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g than increased their dose by at least 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g. SMART, Symbicort&#x000ae; (budesonide/formoterol) maintenance and reliever therapy; BDP, beclomethasone dipropionate</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725-f5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Safety</title><p>All three treatments were well tolerated and there were no notable between-group differences in the number or severity of adverse events. The most frequently reported adverse events were upper respiratory tract infection, pharyngitis and nasopharyngitis. The incidence of pharmacologically predictable adverse events related to ICS and LABA use was low and comparable in all treatment groups.</p><p>Serious adverse events were uncommon and their incidence was comparable across all three treatment groups: 32 patients (3%) in the salmeterol/fluticasone group, 39 patients (4%) in the fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol group and 31 patients (3%) in the SMART group experienced such events. Four serious adverse events were considered by the investigator to be causally related to the study drug: three in the SMART group (pneumonia, gastritis and asthma) and one in the salmeterol/fluticasone group (asthma).</p><p>Two deaths occurred during the study, one in the SMART group (respiratory failure) and one in the salmeterol/fluticasone group (cardiac failure). Neither death was considered by the investigator to be causally related to the study drug.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This study validates the concept of SMART. Reducing the maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol by 50% and using budesonide/formoterol as reliever medication instead of terbutaline reduces the risk and rate of severe exacerbations in adults and adolescents with asthma compared with a higher maintenance dose of fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol or salmeterol/fluticasone. Other measures of daily asthma control were similar across the three treatment groups. This improvement in the outcome of asthma treatment was seen even though the total dose of ICS administered using the SMART regimen was 25% lower in BDP equivalents than those administered in the fixed-dose regimens. Thus, while conventional fixed-dose combination therapy can provide well-controlled asthma for many patients, similar improvements can be achieved with the SMART approach while further reducing exacerbations and drug load.</p><p>The reduction in exacerbations and associated medical care was substantial. Patients in the SMART group had 28&#x02013;39% fewer exacerbations than those in the fixed-dose groups. Extrapolating these 6-month data to a 1-year period suggests that treating 100 matched patients for 1 year with SMART compared with fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone and fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol would prevent 15 and 9 severe exacerbations respectively (the number needed to treat to prevent one exacerbation was 7 and 11 respectively). There were fewer exacerbations requiring hospitalisation or ER treatment in the SMART group, with such events occurring on 61% fewer days compared with salmeterol/fluticasone and on 38% fewer days compared with fixed double-dose budesonide/formoterol. Exacerbations leading to ER treatment or hospitalisation were approximately 1 day longer on average (based on the number of days with these events) in the fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone vs. the SMART group.</p><p>It seems unlikely that the reduced number of SMART patients who still experienced exacerbations did so as a result of using a maintenance dose that was too low. All patients using fixed-combination ICS/LABA in our study received the equivalent of the maximally effective dose used in the landmark FACET exacerbation study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>). With SMART, the average dose used approached 75% of the FACET dose. Nevertheless, SMART resulted in further reductions in exacerbations of all types vs. both fixed-dose groups. This suggests that the SMART approach has exceeded a previous gold standard for exacerbation control, while reducing overall steroid and LABA doses.</p><p>The precise reason for the overall reduction in exacerbations with the SMART approach remains to be fully elucidated. Temporary dose increases resulting from as-needed formoterol and budesonide are likely to contribute to the overall efficacy of this treatment. As-needed treatment immediately following exposure to environmental triggers that lead to a temporary loss of symptom control is likely to result in an increase in controller therapy in line with disease activity. During periods when asthma control is stable, with no need for symptom relief (56% of study days), patients using the SMART approach default solely to maintenance budesonide/formoterol, but at half the daily dose compared with the fixed-dose regimen. Thus, maintenance plus as-needed budesonide/formoterol responds more effectively and efficiently to the natural variations in asthma control that are evident even when using an ICS/LABA regimen at a higher daily dose.</p><p>Timely increases in the ICS dose have been suggested as the defining feature of SMART (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>). Thus, budesonide-containing reliever therapy can ensure that an increase in anti-inflammatory therapy is delivered as required during periods of deteriorating symptoms and increased need for reliever medication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>). In our study, SMART patients used more budesonide/formoterol than the fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol group on only 13% of days, with half the dose used on 56% of days. This suggests that the timing of the dose increase, not the overall dose, is of greater importance. Whether this benefit is related to dose clustering of the as-needed ICS over a spread of days, or to the more efficient spread of the dose throughout the day during periods of poor control, is not clear.</p><p>Studies have shown that increasing the dose and frequency of administration of ICS improves asthma control in patients with acute worsenings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>). As lung tissue concentrations of ICS decline between maintenance doses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>), as-needed ICS may restore concentrations when the level of ICS can be suboptimal. In contrast, approaches that rely on a significant deterioration in asthma symptoms and action plans that instruct patients to double their ICS dose without an increase in dose frequency have been demonstrated to be wholly ineffective at preventing exacerbations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>).</p><p>Marked improvements in daily symptom control were seen in all three treatment groups, despite patients in the SMART group using a lower maintenance dose of ICS/LABA. Compared with run-in, patients in all groups experienced similar improvements in asthma control and quality of life (assessed by questionnaires) and more asthma-control days and fewer asthma-related awakenings (assessed by daily diaries). The increase in day-to-day asthma control seen in all three groups can be extrapolated to at least 130 extra days per year with full symptom control without the use of reliever medication and at least 64 extra nights per year without awakenings. There was no evidence of any clinically relevant between-group differences in any of these control measures. Numbers of days with symptom flares (mild exacerbation days) were equally distributed among the three treatment groups. Furthermore, no differences in lung function were detected between the treatment groups, despite lower use of bronchodilator therapy (maintenance and as needed) in the SMART group. The mean daily ICS dose in BDP equivalents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) was approximately 750 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g in the SMART group vs. 1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g in both fixed-dose groups. In total, only eight SMART patients (&#x0003c; 1%) used a mean dose of budesonide equivalent to &#x0003e; 2000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day of BDP. The majority of SMART patients used less ICS and less LABA than in the fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol group, i.e. for every SMART patient who took 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day of budesonide/formoterol more than in the fixed-dose group, there were nine SMART patients using at least 160/4.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/day less. The fact that day-to-day symptom control was similar in all three groups, even with the clear difference observed in severe exacerbation rates, serves as a reminder that these measures reflect different aspects of asthma control, both of which need to be considered when evaluating asthma management programmes. Our results show the improved control seen with as-needed budesonide/formoterol using the SMART concept vs. fixed-dose ICS/LABA + SABA therapy is greater for exacerbations than for minor symptoms. Minor symptoms dictate the need for an increase in as-needed therapy to a similar extent in all treatment groups, but with the SMART asthma management approach this leads to an increase in anti-inflammatory therapy at the right time, resulting in fewer exacerbations.</p><p>Although there were no clinically important differences between the two fixed-dose groups in the majority of outcomes, one clinically relevant and statistically significant advantage of budesonide/formoterol was observed. Patients treated with fixed-dose budesonide/formoterol had 32% fewer exacerbations requiring hospitalisation/ER treatment vs. those in the salmeterol/fluticasone group. It is noteworthy that this is the largest study ever performed with two fixed-dose ICS/LABA combinations and, as such, may be the first study able to detect such differences. A similar trend was seen in a smaller study (approximately 200 patients in each group) in which three vs. eight events required hospitalisation/ER treatment in patients treated with the same fixed dose of budesonide/formoterol or salmeterol/fluticasone respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>). The reasons for this difference remain unclear and may require further exploratory analysis. One possible reason may be that formoterol, a full <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist, is more efficacious than salmeterol, a partial <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>2</sub>-agonist, during periods of increased inflammation or challenge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>). Another factor may be the beneficial effects on neutrophilic inflammation that have been described for formoterol but to a lesser extent for salmeterol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>).</p><p>In a controlled clinical setting, SMART has previously been shown to improve asthma control compared with the same maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol plus terbutaline for relief (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>). In a study allowing titration of the maintenance dose as judged appropriate by the treating physician, SMART patients had fewer exacerbations and better asthma control than those receiving salmeterol/fluticasone up to a dose of 50/500 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g bid (40% of patients) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). Together these studies suggest that SMART is uniquely effective at reducing exacerbations and their associated morbidity compared with fixed-dose ICS/LABA, even at a higher daily dose. The study by Vogelmeier et al. was performed open label to allow easier maintenance-dose titration; we have now demonstrated in a very large double-blind study that SMART leads to fewer exacerbations with no increase in fluctuations of daily asthma control compared with a twofold higher maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol or a corresponding dose of salmeterol/fluticasone. The SMART approach has also been demonstrated to deliver significant cost savings compared with the higher maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol or salmeterol/fluticasone plus terbutaline as needed, when applying 2004 UK unit costs to the present dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, patients who were infrequent users of reliever medication were excluded after the run-in period. This may have excluded a small minority of patients for whom the benefit of SMART is unknown. Nonetheless, a recent survey of 1921 patients using regular ICS or ICS/LABA medication has highlighted that 71% of these patients used their reliever medication every day and 47% had experienced one or more exacerbations in the previous year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), suggesting that the results of the present study have wide-reaching applicability to real-life asthma. Finally, this study, in addition to previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>), has confirmed that the SMART treatment approach is well tolerated with no increase in asthma-related events of any type compared with higher doses of ICS alone or an alternative combination ICS/LABA regimen.</p><p>In conclusion, compared with a twofold higher fixed maintenance dose of budesonide/formoterol or a corresponding dose of salmeterol/fluticasone plus SABA for relief, SMART reduces the incidence of severe asthma exacerbations and maintains similar daily asthma control at a lower overall drug load. With this combination of increased efficacy and simplicity, the SMART approach represents a significant improvement over fixed, twice-daily combinations of higher-dose ICS/LABA, which have until now been regarded as the most effective way to manage moderate and severe persistent asthma.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the study investigators for their outstanding work in conducting the trial. We thank Anette Bj&#x000e4;rdahlen (AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden), the study team leader; Stefan Peterson (AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden), who performed all data analyses; Tomas LG Andersson (AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden), who contributed to the interpretation of the results and the compilation of the manuscript; Allan Harris (AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden), who was responsible for the development of the study concept and Deirdre Carman (Adelphi Communications Ltd) who provided medical writing support on behalf of AstraZeneca. This study was funded by AstraZeneca, Lund, Sweden.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aalbers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adjustable maintenance dosing with budesonide/formoterol compared with fixed-dose salmeterol/fluticasone in moderate to severe asthma</article-title><source>Curr Med Res Opin</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lalloo</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Budesonide and formoterol in a single inhaler improves asthma control compared with increasing the dose of corticosteroid in adults with mild-to-moderate asthma</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2003</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12740264</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combined salmeterol 50 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g and fluticasone propionate 250 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g in the diskus device for the treatment of asthma</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673196</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Worldwide severity and control of asthma in children and adults: the global asthma insights and reality surveys</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241342</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Attitudes and actions of asthma patients on regular maintenance therapy: the INSPIRE study</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16772035</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-acting beta 2-agonist and oral corticosteroid use in asthma patients prescribed either concurrent beclomethasone and long-acting beta 2-agonist or salmeterol/fluticasone propionate combination</article-title><source>Int J Clin Pract</source><year>2005</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15854190</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Self-management education and regular practitioner review for adults with asthma</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>CD001117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of asthma and asthma action plans in South Australia: population surveys from 1990 to 2001</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2003</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12741932</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Byrne</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Budesonide/formoterol combination therapy as both maintenance and reliever medication in asthma</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502112</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Budesonide/formoterol in a single inhaler for maintenance and relief in mild-to-moderate asthma: a randomized, double-blind trial</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2006</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478838</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of budesonide in combination with formoterol for reliever therapy in asthma exacerbations: a randomised controlled, double-blind study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16935685</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogelmeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Budesonide/formoterol maintenance and reliever therapy: an effective asthma treatment option</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16264042</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab>Global Initiative for Asthma</collab><source>Global Strategy for Asthma Management and Prevention 2006</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ginasthma.com">http://www.ginasthma.com</ext-link> (accessed January 2007)</comment></citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EXCEL: a randomised trial comparing salmeterol/fluticasone propionate and formoterol/budesonide combinations in adults with persistent asthma</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16675212</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="other"><collab>American Thoracic Society</collab><article-title>Standards for the diagnosis and care of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and asthma</article-title><source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source><year>1987</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3605835</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical equivalence of salmeterol/fluticasone propionate in combination (50/100 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g twice daily) when administered via a chlorofluorocarbon-free metered dose inhaler or dry powder inhaler to patients with mild-to-moderate asthma</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11217910</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Noord</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical equivalence of a salmeterol/fluticasone propionate combination product (50/500 mcg) delivered via a chlorofluorocarbon-free metered-dose inhaler with the Diskus (TM) in patients with moderate to severe asthma</article-title><source>Clin Drug Investig</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quanjer</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lung volumes and forced ventilatory flows. Report Working Party Standardization of Lung Function Tests, European Community for Steel and Coal. Official Statement of the European Respiratory Society</article-title><source>Eur Respir J Suppl</source><year>1993</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8499054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polgar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pulmonary Function Testing in Children: Techniques and Standards</source><year>1971</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>W.B. Saunders Company</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of a questionnaire to measure asthma control</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>1999</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10573240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measurement properties and interpretation of three shortened versions of the asthma control questionnaire</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15823451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation of a standardized version of the Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1999</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10334138</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tables of the number of patients required in clinical trials using the logrank test</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>1982</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7187087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining a minimal important change in a disease-specific Quality of Life Questionnaire</article-title><source>J Clin Epidemiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8283197</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of inhaled formoterol and budesonide on exacerbations of asthma. Formoterol and Corticosteroids Establishing Therapy (FACET) International Study Group</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9358137</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single inhaler for asthma</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15640369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teaching old drugs new tricks: asthma therapy adjusted by patient perception or noninvasive markers</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15738278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tattersfield</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exacerbations of asthma: a descriptive study of 425 severe exacerbations. The FACET International Study Group</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10430734</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foresi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose budesonide with the addition of an increased dose during exacerbations is effective in long-term asthma control. On behalf of the Italian Study Group</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2000</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669688</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller-Larsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reversible fatty acid conjugation of budesonide. Novel mechanism for prolonged retention of topically applied steroid in airway tissue</article-title><source>Drug Metab Dispos</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660844</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jendbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of budesonide and its major ester metabolite after inhalation and intravenous administration of budesonide in the rat</article-title><source>Drug Metab Dispos</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11302946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Doubling the dose of inhaled corticosteroid to prevent asthma exacerbations: randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2004</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14751699</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>FitzGerald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Doubling the dose of budesonide versus maintenance treatment in asthma exacerbations</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2004</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15223858</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmqvist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the relative efficacy of formoterol and salmeterol in asthmatic patients</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10390407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Veen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of salmeterol and formoterol in attenuating airway responses to short-acting beta2-agonists</article-title><source>Pulm Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749831</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tintinger</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the effects of selective and non-selective beta-adrenoceptor agonists on the pro-inflammatory activities of human neutrophils in vivo</article-title><source>Inflammation</source><year>2000</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="b37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Budesonide/formoterol (B/F) as maintenance and relief for asthma improves efficacy and is cost-saving versus a higher maintenance dose of B/F or salmeterol/fluticasone (S/F)</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2006</year><volume>28</volume><issue>Suppl. 50</issue><fpage>P1274</fpage></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The following supplementary material is available for this article online:</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Slideshow S1</label><caption><p>Effect of budesonide/formoterol maintenance and reliever therapy on asthma exacerbations.</p></caption><media xlink:role="associated-file" xlink:href="ijcp0061-0725_p1.ppt" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x1a53f30N0x32f58f0" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"/></supplementary-material><p>This material is available as part of the online article from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blackwell-synergy.com">http://www.blackwell-synergy.com</ext-link></p></sec></back></article>





