<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diacare</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dcare</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20067958</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2845038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc09-1578</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Emerging Treatments and Technologies</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy and Safety of Lacosamide in Painful Diabetic Neuropathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FRCP(E)</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hidv&#x000e9;gi</surname><given-names>Tibor</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gurieva</surname><given-names>Irina</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bongardt</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Freynhagen</surname><given-names>Rainer</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><degrees>PHD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sommerville</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><collab>on behalf of the Lacosamide SP743 Study Group<xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref></collab></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Institute for Clinical Diabetology, German Diabetes Center at the Heinrich Heine University, Leibniz Center for Diabetes Research, and the Department of Metabolic Diseases, University Hospital, D&#x000fc;sseldorf, Germany; </aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Petz Alad&#x000e1;r County Teaching Hospital, Department of Metabolism and Diabetes, Gy&#x00151;r, Hungary; </aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Federal State Institution, Federal Bureau Medical Social Expertise, Moscow, Russia; </aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Schwarz Pharma, UCB Group, Monheim, Germany; </aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup>Department of Anaesthesiology, Critical Care Medicine, Pain Therapy &#x00026; Palliative Care, Pain Center Lake Starnberg, Benedictus Krankenhaus, Tutzing, Germany; </aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup>Schwarz Biosciences, UCB Group, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Dan Ziegler, <email>dan.ziegler@ddz.uni-duesseldorf.de</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="FN1"><p>*Members of the SP743 Study Group are listed in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1"><sc>appendix</sc></xref>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2010 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zdc00410000839.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>To evaluate efficacy and safety of lacosamide compared with placebo in painful diabetic polyneuropathy.</p></sec><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>Diabetic patients with at least moderate neuropathic pain were randomized to placebo or lacosamide 400 (in a slow or standard titration) or 600 mg/day over 6-week titration and 12-week maintenance periods. Primary efficacy criterion was intra-individual change in average daily Numeric Pain Rating Scale score from baseline to the last 4 weeks.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>For the primary end point, pain reduction was numerically but not statistically greater with lacosamide compared with placebo (400 mg/day, <italic>P</italic> = 0.12; 600 mg/day, <italic>P</italic> = 0.18). Both doses were significantly more effective compared with placebo over the titration (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006), maintenance (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01, <italic>P</italic> = 0.005), and entire treatment periods (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02). Safety profiles between titration schemes were similar.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Lacosamide reduced neuropathic pain and was well tolerated in diabetic patients, but the primary efficacy criterion was not met, possibly due to an increased placebo response over the last 4 weeks.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Up to one in four patients with diabetes may be affected by chronic diabetic painful neuropathy (DPN) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>) and suffer substantial morbidity and impaired quality of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Because the current treatment options are limited, there is continued need for new therapeutic approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Lacosamide is an anticonvulsant with a unique mode of action, selectively enhancing slow inactivation of voltage-gated sodium channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). This trial was one of three similarly designed placebo-controlled, parallel-group trials to evaluate the efficacy of lacosamide in DPN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) using 400 mg/day (two titration schemes) and 600 mg/day.</p><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>This trial (SP743, ClinicalTrials.gov identifier NCT00238524), conducted December 2003 to January 2005 at 52 European sites, was approved by Institutional Review Boards and met with the International Conference on Harmonisation&#x02013;Good Clinical Practice (ICH-GCP) guidelines and local laws. All patients signed written informed consent before participation.</p><sec><title>Study population</title><p>Eligibility criteria were as follows: patients aged &#x02265;18 years with type 1 or type 2 diabetes, symptomatic DPN for 6 months to 5 years (score &#x02265;4 on an 11-point Numeric Pain Rating Scale [NPRS]), and A1C &#x0003c;12%). Exclusion criteria are described in supplemental Appendix A, which is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dc09-1578/DC1">http://care.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dc09-1578/DC1</ext-link>. Concomitant acetaminophen &#x02264;2 g/day was permitted as rescue medication.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial design</title><p>This 18-week, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial began with a 1-week washout and a 1-week baseline period for pain assessments. Eligible patients were randomized (1:2:2) to placebo or oral lacosamide, 400 or 600 mg/day, and then entered a 6-week titration period followed by a 12-week maintenance period. To ensure blinding, trial medication and packaging were identical in appearance, and all dosing was twice daily. The 400 mg/day group was further randomized to receive slow titration (100 mg/day for 3 weeks, followed by weekly increases of 100 mg/day, to 400 mg/day target dose at week 6) or a standard titration (100 mg/day, with weekly increases of 100 mg/day, to 400 mg/day target dose for titration weeks 4&#x02013;6). The 600 mg/day group followed standard titration increasing by 100 mg/day each week. No back titration was allowed.</p></sec><sec><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was intra-individual change in average daily (24-h) pain score (11-point NPRS; 0 = no pain, 10 = worst possible pain) from baseline to average score over the last 4 weeks of the maintenance period. Secondary measures included within-subject change in average daily pain score from baseline to each trial period (titration, maintenance, and entire treatment). Additional secondary measures are described in supplemental Appendix A. Safety evaluations on all patients receiving one or more doses of trial medication (safety set) included adverse event reporting, withdrawals, clinically relevant laboratory changes, 12-lead electrocardiogram, vital signs, and physical and neurological examinations. Statistical methods are described in supplemental Appendix A.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Of 513 patients screened, 357 were randomized and received one or more doses of trial medication, 355 comprised the ITT population, and 246 completed the trial (CONSORT diagram shown in supplemental Appendix Figure B1). All groups showed similar demographic and baseline characteristics, although numerically, more patients in the placebo group reported severe pain (NPRS &#x02265;8) at baseline (supplemental Appendix Table B1). Medical history and concomitant diseases were similar across treatment groups and were as expected in a DPN population. Concomitant medication use was similar across groups.</p><p>Reductions in average daily pain scores from baseline to the last 4 weeks of the maintenance period (primary end point) were greater in both the lacosamide 400 and 600 mg/day groups compared with placebo, although differences were not statistically significant, possibly related to increased placebo effect toward the end of the trial (<italic>P</italic> = 0.12, <italic>P</italic> = 0.18; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). However, both lacosamide doses were significantly more effective than placebo in reducing average daily pain scores when assessed for the titration period (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and maintenance period (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01), and entire treatment period (titration period + maintenance period; <italic>P</italic> = 0.03, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02; detailed description provided in supplemental Appendix Table C1).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mean change from baseline in average daily pain score at each trial visit (weeks 2, 4, 5, 6, 10, 14, and 18) for observed cases (OC: patients still in the trial at the time of the clinic visit or during that visit interval) and last observation carried forward (LOCF). BL, baseline; LCM, lacosamide; MP, maintenance period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdc0041081550001"/></fig><p>In addition to the consistency of effect on NPRS scores through the total treatment period with lacosamide, persistent and clinically relevant effects were observed for the secondary efficacy measures such as patients' perceptions of pain using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS), the Patients' Global Impression of Change (PGIC), and pain interference with sleep and activity (supplemental Appendix C). Generally, pain reductions were only slightly higher in the lacosamide 600 mg/day group than the lacosamide 400 mg/day group and may have been affected by higher dropout rates and less tolerability with the 600 mg/day dose.</p><p>Adverse events occurring in &#x02265;5% of lacosamide-treated patients included dizziness, fatigue, nausea, vertigo, headache, and vomiting; except for fatigue, these adverse events appeared to be dose related (supplemental Appendix Table D1). Changes in laboratory variables, vital signs, body weight, and findings from physical and neurological examinations revealed no issues of clinical concern. Adverse event incidence was similar between the 400 mg/day slow and standard titration groups during the titration period (slow, 46% [35/77]; standard, 49% [36/73]). Adverse events resulting in withdrawal occurred at an incidence of 13.0% versus 8.2% for the 400 mg/day standard and slow titration groups, respectively.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>In this trial, lacosamide did not result in statistically significant pain reductions over placebo for the primary outcome. However, lacosamide showed a durability of effect that was sustained and significantly greater than placebo through the titration, maintenance, and entire treatment periods. Persistent and clinically relevant effects were also observed for the secondary efficacy measures (PGIC, VAS, and pain interference with sleep and activity). Titration schemes did not affect tolerability.</p><p>The increased placebo response observed at the end of the maintenance period, with almost a quarter of the placebo group experiencing a &#x02265;50% reduction in pain score in the last 4 weeks, may have contributed to the lack of statistical significance in the primary end point. High placebo responses are not unusual in neuropathic pain studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Because of the relatively long titration, this trial is among the longest conducted in patients with DPN. In trials of DPN, placebo response does not plateau, but increases over time, such that longer trials are at greater risk for decreased separation of drug effect from placebo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, lacosamide resulted in numerically greater pain reductions over placebo, but for the primary efficacy variable of change in average pain score from baseline to the last 4 weeks of maintenance period, the differences were not statistically significant, possibly related to a marked increase in placebo response during the last 4 weeks of the trial.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Online-Only Appendix</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_33_4_839__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
                   xlink:href="supp_dc09-1578_dc09-1578_online_appendix.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Clinical trial reg. no.: NCT00238524, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;advertisement&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors acknowledge the contributions made by members of the SP743 multicenter trial team. Barbara Stegmann, MD, PhD; Brigitte Koch, PhD; Stephan Thierfelder, PhD; Christine Rauschkolb, MD, PhD; and David Sen, PhD, assisted with the design of the trial and provided clinical and statistical oversight. On behalf of the sponsor, Jennifer Kemp, PhD, and Heather Bell, MSc, helped draft the manuscript and Andrea Eggert, PharmD, BCPP, and Allison Coppola provided editorial assistance. Prescott Medical Communications Group provided editorial and formatting assistance. Schwarz Pharma, UCB Group, Monheim, Germany, provided the trial supplies, and Schwarz Biosciences, UCB Group, Monheim, Germany, sponsored and funded the trial.</p><p>In the past 3 years, D.Z. has received research support, consulting, or speaking fees from Lilly, Boehringer, Pfizer, Meda, Merck, Bayer, Nycomed, Gr&#x000fc;nenthal, sanofi-aventis, Eisai, Mundipharma, and Schwarz Pharma/UCB Group, and R.F. has received the same fees from Gr&#x000fc;nenthal, Jansen-Cilag, Lilly/Boehringer, Mundipharma, Organon, Pfizer, and Schwarz Pharma/UCB Group. K.S. is presently Vice President of Clinical Development at King Pharmaceuticals and has been in the position since March 2008. King Pharmaceuticals is a publicly traded U.S. corporation actively engaged in the development and sale of specialty branded pharmaceutical products, including products indicated for the treatment of pain. K.S. was an employee of the sponsor through the duration of the trial. I.G. has received research support, consulting, or speaking fees from Lilly, Pfizer, Meda, Pliva, Woervag Pharma, Nycomed, sanofi-aventis, and Schwarz Pharma/UCB Group. S.B. and D.S. are employees of the sponsor. No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p></ack><app-group><app id="app1"><title>APPENDIX</title><p>Members of the SP743 multicenter trial team include the following: C. Mathieu, Leuven, Belgium; L. Van Gaal, Antwerp, Belgium; F. Duyck, Roeselare, Belgium; A. Verhaegen, Merksem, Belgium; B. Vets, Bonheiden, Belgium; J. Hovorka, Prague, Czech Republic; R. Mazanec, Prague, Czech Republic; D. Dolezil, Ostrava-Poruba, Czech Republic; P. Valensi, Bondy, France; C. Le Devehat, Nevers, France; L. Geffray, Lisieux, France; J. von Hubbenet, Hamburg, Germany; J. Jansen, Berlin, Germany; C. Klein, K&#x000fc;nzing, Germany; T. Drescher, Stuhr-Brinkum, Germany; A. Herzner, Hamburg, Germany; R. Bodenschatz, Mittweida, Germany; A. Pfeiffer, Berlin, Germany; R. Nischik, Leipzig, Germany; B. Bergtholdt, Berlin, Germany; E. Boenninghoff, Beckum, Germany; H. Stahl, Leipzig, Germany; A. Holst, Hamburg, Germany; P. Franz, Berlin, Germany; R. Lehmann, Berlin, Germany; G. Jermendy, Budapest, Hungary; G. Winkler, Budapest, Hungary; V. Spallone, Roma, Italy; G. Comi, Milan, Italy; J. Banga, Utrecht, the Netherlands; A. Mikolajczyk-Swatko, Lodz, Poland; W. Fryze, Gdansk, Poland; M. Arciszewska, Bialystok, Poland; E. Semetkowska-Jurkiewicz, Gdansk, Poland; M. Polaszewska-Muszynska, Bydgoszcz, Poland; J. Skowron, Cz&#x00119;stochowa, Poland; D. Cheta, Bucharest, Romania; N. Hancu, Cluj-Napoca, Romania; C. Ionescu-Tirgoviste, Bucharest, Romania; G. Negri&#x000e7;sanu, Timisoara, Romania; N. Verbovaya, Samara, Russia; A. Zalevskaya, St. Petersburg, Russia; A. Ametov, Moscow, Russia; I. Dedov, Moscow, Russia; M. Ansiferov, Moscow, Russia; F.J. Salvador Rodriguez, Pamplona, Spain; A. Baksi, Newport, U.K.; D. Price, Swansea, U.K.; K. Simpson, Leeds, U.K.; and G. Rayman, Ipswich, U.K.</p></app></app-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The prevalence, severity, and impact of painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1518</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickhaus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mielck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><collab>KORA Study Group.</collab><article-title>KORA Study Group. Neuropathic pain in diabetes, prediabetes and normal glucose tolerance: the MONICA/KORA Augsburg Surveys S2 and S3</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19207236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinik</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Arezzo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bril</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maser</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosenko</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><collab>American Diabetes Association.</collab><article-title>Diabetic neuropathies: a statement by the American Diabetes Association</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>956</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Painful diabetic neuropathy: advantage of novel drugs over old drugs?</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 3</issue>):<fpage>S414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19875591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hovinga</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>SPM-927 (Schwarz Pharma)</article-title>. <source>IDrugs</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12789603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f6;hr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Heers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>The investigational anticonvulsant lacosamide selectively enhances slow inactivation of voltage-gated sodium channels</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17940193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyreuther</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Callizot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f6;hr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Antinociceptive efficacy of lacosamide in a rat model for painful diabetic neuropathy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>539</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16682022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyreuther</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebsf&#x000e4;nger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharfenecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000f6;hr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Lacosamide: a review of preclinical properties</article-title>. <source>CNS Drug Rev</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17461888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaibani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fares</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Selam</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Arslanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Lacosamide in painful diabetic neuropathy: an 18-week double-blind placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19409861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wymer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Lacosamide SP742 Study Group.</collab><article-title>Efficacy and safety of lacosamide in diabetic neuropathic pain: an 18-week double-blind placebo-controlled trial of fixed-dose regimens</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>376</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19454870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thienel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwabe</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijapurkar</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Topiramate Diabetic Neuropathic Pain Study Group.</collab><article-title>Topiramate in painful diabetic polyneuropathy: findings from three double-blind placebo-controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingery</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>A critical review of controlled clinical trials for peripheral neuropathic pain and complex regional pain syndromes</article-title>. <source>Pain</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9415498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnerup</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Clinical trial outcome in neuropathic pain: relationship to study characteristics</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quessy</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowbotham</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> <article-title>Placebo response in neuropathic pain trials</article-title>. <source>Pain</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18706762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>